Your body produces a nutrient that you
can increase through your diet. And a
big study shows that flooding this
nutrient into cancer cells leads to some
remarkable switches. Specifically, it
stresses and kills cancer cells. The
idea is that as many cancers feed on
sugar, glucose for energy among other
reasons, we can take advantage of that
preference by introducing a particular
fat. But it can't be just any fat
because this one is special due to its
size and its shape. You see, a century
ago, a cancer concept called the Warberg
effect was introduced. The Warberg
effect is when cells turn cancerous,
they also reduce their dependence on fat
metabolism for energy and focus heavily
on glucose for energy. The same blood
glucose that's courarssing through your
veins right now. There are multiple
reasons cancer cells switch, but I have
a lot of incredible things to show you,
so we'll leave it there for now. Just
knowing that they do. Researchers can
measure how aggressive cancer cells have
shifted to glucose metabolism by
measuring the production of the first
step in the glucose metabolizing system
called glycolysis. This first step, the
moment that glucose enters the cell, is
to trap glucose into the cancer cell by
adding a tag, a phosphate to it,
creating a new molecule called glucose 6
phosphate. We can see that data here.
We're measuring G6P or glucose 6
phosphate levels. So, the higher the
bar, the more G6P. The cancer cells are
exposed to high glucose, primed for the
Warberg effect, or low glucose
environment, disabling the Warberg
effect. Clearly the high glucose leads
to a significant increase. In fact, as
further evidenced here as the
researchers have added a mitotraer, a
die to the cancer cells to identify two
things. One, the total number of
mitochondria in green and two, the
oxidative mitochondria, meaning
mitochondria that are producing cellular
energy, likely through fat metabolism.
Remember, that shouldn't be happening.
If the cancer cells are undergoing the
Warberg effect, then there's an overlap
in yellow to identify both at once. We
have the low glucose condition, the high
glucose condition, non-cancerous colon
cells from humans and mice. The cancer
cells are human, FYI. And we can clearly
see that mitochondria green exist in
every single condition, but the red is
largely extinguished when cancer cells
are given a high glucose environment,
again indicating the Warberg effect.
This is also measured quantitatively in
the bar graphs to the right. The thing
is researchers aren't just concerned
with the shifts in metabolism but also
how cancer cells change their gene
expression as in how cancer cells read
their genes to produce the appropriate
proteins to function. Unfortunately for
cancer cells, researchers have
identified fat that interferes with the
whole cancer process. That fat is called
butyrate and it's unique in some key
ways that relate to its structure and
size that lend itself well to hurting
cancer cells. But the way that it hurts
cancer cells is actually heavily gene
related. Still, let me throw a wrench
into the statement butyrate hurts cancer
cells. Does it though? If we pop open
these data, we're looking at the sheer
number of cells at varying levels of
butyrate exposure. So listed on the
horizontal axis. As we're talking about
primarily about cancer cells, we want
those bars to go down. There are however
three conditions. A Warberg effect, high
glucose cancer cells, a non-warberg
cancer cells exposed to low glucose, and
a third condition which we actually
won't worry about. It's a lactate
dehydrogenase knockdown. Focus on the
two non-black bars and compare against
the zero butyrate condition. Notice how
yes, greater butyrate concentrations
seem to reduce cancer cell count, but
what's going on with the lower
concentrations? There seems to be an
increase in cancer cell count, meaning
butyrate is stimulating cancer cells.
Actually, we see that across multiple
lines of evidence, including DNA
synthesis. Keep in mind, cancer cells
when they duplicate have to also
duplicate their genome. So, the
researchers add a DNA tag called BRDU
that is incorporated into the DNA. Here
we again see the low concentrations of
butyrate stimulate DNA synthesis in
cancer cells compared to when butyrate
is not there. Yet at higher
concentrations it reduces DNA synthesis.
We'll come back to why butyrate both
stimulates cancer cells and hurts them
including what to do about it. Before
that though I'd like to show you a final
experiment on the stress that cancer
experiences with butyrate. This is
called an anexin 5 experiment.
Essentially, an XN5 is a protein that
binds these molecules found on the cell
membrane called phosphatidal serirines.
In healthy cells, phosphatidal serarine
is found on the inside of the cell
membrane. But in early stages of
programmed cell death, the cell will
expose the inner section of the membrane
to the outside. It literally flips the
section of the cell membrane to expose
them to the outside environment. I think
that's such a cool experiment.
That's where NX and 5 can bind these
molecules. Scientists can detect that
and determine which cells are dying and
which cells are alive. There's another
component called PI or propidium iodide,
but we'll focus on the former. Anyway,
here we're looking at an XN5 and PI
standing by flowcytometry. Essentially,
all you need to know is that we're
looking is if the cells identified by
the colors are trending toward the top
right quadrant, that indicates more cell
death as there's more and five and pi
present on and in the cells. We can
clearly see that greater butyrate leads
to more cancer cells suffering death.
Off with their heads. Okay, so the
butyrate paradox. You have to flood the
cancer cells with butyrate to knock them
off kilter because if you don't, you may
be helping them. Now, let's figure out
what butyrate is doing inside the cancer
cells that's leading to these effects
and then we'll come to understand what
to do. I briefly mentioned that cancer
cells also change their gene expression
and one of the ways that they do that is
through the process called acetylation.
Your genes and by extension cancerous
genes are wrapped up around these
protein structures called histones. The
cell can add or remove tags known as
acetal tags to the histones which
changes if the histones are closed up or
open for the genes around them to be
read by gene reading complexes. However,
in certain cancer cells there is reduced
acetylation to lock up the certain genes
typically anti-cancer genes. However,
what happens when the cells take up
butyrate? Well, look here. We're looking
at the general acetylation levels up top
and the histones themselves in the
middle and a control protein on the
bottom. Unless you have experience with
that western blood analysis, I'll just
focus on the top two. We're measuring
the relative and absolute levels of
acetylation, these tags on the histones.
When the cancer cells are exposed to
butyrate on the bottom, the darker and
larger the splotch, the more there is.
So clearly at the higher butyrate
concentrations there's more universal
acetylation and possibly opening of the
histones. But we don't need to stop
there because there's histone
independent acetylation and there's a
powerful protein in your cells that acts
as a master anti-tumor factor. It's
called p53.
Unfortunately in many cancers p-53 is
inactivated in some way. However,
acetylating p-53 can enhance its
stability and DNA binding abilities. So,
what happens? The same principles. Up
top, we have the acetylated version, the
more stable version, and below that is
the actual protein, not necessarily
acetylated. So, there's no change in the
actual protein, but there's an increase
in the stable version. That indicates
that butyrate not only influences the
genes, but also affects the anti-cancer
proteins inside the cell. Okay, enough
cell biology. Why does butyrate promote
cancer and yet also shut it down? And
how do we use this information? Or if
you're an uber nerd like me, there's two
distinct effects that butyrate has in
your cells based on the concentration
found around your cells. And there's
some people who don't generate much
butyrate, even when they eat the right
foods. And more specifics on those foods
and even butyrate dosing. I'll be
discussing some of that coming up. But
if you want even more detailed analysis
with even more specific takeaways,
consider joining the Physionic Insiders.
It's my premium research platform that
gives you full access to all my work,
plus a private podcast, live sessions
with me, protocols and guides, weekly
articles delivered to you, and more.
It's a steal, and I'm proud to
continuously work to improve it. You can
check it out in the description box. We
saw multiple lines of evidence that
butyrate increases cancer cell number
and then suddenly crushes them. Well,
we've been focused on colon cells. Even
the cancer cells are colon cells. And if
we look at the data on the colon and the
general butyrate concentrations, they
change based on the section of the colon
that you're referring to here. The
proximal here, the medial about here,
and the distal here. So that might raise
this concern that cancer will only be
killed by the proximal sections and not
be killed in the medial or distal. Well,
this is where the researchers have some
words of wisdom because they address two
things. One, if we zoom into your colon,
there's these crypts which have been
made by an assortment of cells. The top
part is made up of differentiated,
meaning cells that have chosen their
job, epithelial cells, and the lower
sections are a mixture of cells. But
this is where cancer usually occurs
because there are stem cells here too.
The researchers point out that there's
also lower butyrate concentrations here
too, which again raises this worry that
butyrate could be feeding the cancer.
Then here's the thing, though. Cancer
cells undergoing the Warberg effect
don't metabolize butyrate even at low
concentration. So butyrate bypasses
metabolism and acts on the genes like we
described with the greater
concentrations of acetal groups on the
appropriate proteins, the histones, p-53
and so on. If we revisit those first
data that scared us, there's a key
factor here that we didn't go over. The
cells undergoing Warberg are diminished
even at low concentrations. It's only
cancer cells forced to stop the Warberg
effect that duplicate more with you with
butyrate addition. We'll come back to
that. Okay. Two, the amount of butyrate
that we produce is quite high assuming
that you're eating the right foods and
likely exceeds throughout the colon the
levels that we have in this study. So
this all means that butyrate
metabolizing capable cells like your
colonocytes get the advantage of a
butyrate boost in proliferation. But
Warberg centric cancer cells have a
disadvantage even at low concentrations,
but even more so at high concentrations.
Still, that leaves us with a few pieces
of context to mention because there's a
few outstanding questions before we
finish our journey here. One, this was
largely in human cells, which we don't
translate to humans directly without
more proof in humans. Fortunately, the
researchers acknowledge that there are
human studies indicating that butyrate
ccentric foods are linked to reduce
cancer. In fact, they even mention a
study where researchers identified
reduced butyrate producing bacteria in
people with colurectal cancer compared
to healthy individuals. This of course
isn't cause and effect evidence, but now
we have multiple lines indicating that
butyrate producing bacteria play a role.
Number two, some cancer feed on fat. So
while yes many cancers undergo this
Warberg effect not all do and in fact
the researchers focused on one type of
colarctal cancer and there are others.
So this seems useful for the majority
but may not be for all. Still there's no
way of knowing until a person has cancer
and the butyrate promoting foods are
consistently linked to reduce cancer.
So, we probably shouldn't worry about
the minority of cases and aim for the
best case. Now, that means if you want
to increase butyrate levels and drown
these types of cancers, you'll want to
eat foods that these bacteria in your
gut take, and turn into butyrate, which
is dietary fiber richch foods. Some
examples are things like green bananas,
plantains, I don't know, onions, garlic,
potatoes, and there are plenty more
sources out there. That said, the main
takeaways here are that for most cancer
types, those feeding on glucose, sugar,
there's some evidence that the short-
chain fat butyrate hurts them and kills
them. However, this may be the opposite
in low doses for nonwarber cancers, a
minority of cancers. Generally, butyrate
stimulating foods high in dietary fiber
are associated with reduced cancer
overall. Now, did you know that while
fiber is an excellent choice for cancer,
there's other gut health supplements and
nutrients that might be detrimental and
make cancer progression worse? Well, now
you do.